Hello, everyone.
My name's Nick Rezai.
I'm here to present From Health
Data to Action: Building AI Agents
that Observe, Reason, and Intervene.
A bit about me.
I'm currently technical
research staff at a Harvard lab.
I'm pursuing a master's of
computational biology at Harvard.
I'm, in the past, been a senior
software engineer at Caltech and
a software engineer at Citibank.
Overview of the presentation.
I'm first gonna discuss how AI can move
beyond just analysis and go into action.
I'm gonna talk about how we can
connect personal data to give better
actions, and then I'm gonna discuss
how we can do those personalized
interventions with skill files A bit
of overview something that's already
pretty common now is people feeding in
their health data to AI agents to then
get some analysis or recommendation.
This has actually been discussed by
Sam Altman in a vi- interview where
people will feed in all their sensor
data and ask ChatGPT for advice.
There's recently been a big wave of
research in the field where people look
at how good ChatGPT is at diagnosing
certain illnesses and then also treatment
planning A bit of the process that
would happen if someone were to put
all their, wearable data into ChatGPT,
they'd first export the Fitbit data
upload the files to, any AI model, saying
ChatGPT for this example, and then ask
for some type of insight afterwards.
And this process is
already relatively common.
It's pretty well discussed online.
There's even MCPs now to
automatically connect Fitbit data.
There's nothing too new here.
The next step that I wanna take this in
is giving the data to ChatGPT or some
AI model and then asking it to do some
type of action to then help you with
the health goal that you want to do.
And this is still a developing field
of how can AI agents go and intervene
on your life given your health goal
and your data And what this would look
like is you feed in your data, you feed
in your exercise goal, you give it to
an AI model, and then from there you
get some type of notification that,
your walks are better, at this time,
or, you're inactive at this time.
And these interventions would
be personalized to your patterns
and your goal as an individual.
So my, notification may be different
from someone else's notification So
what does this process look like?
How do we set this up so we can
start getting these notifications?
And I'm sure as some of you are
already thinking, we close our laptops
every day, our laptop goes to sleep.
So we need some other type of device that
we can, store at home to then sync our
data and then send these notifications.
And then we also want the server to
see past notifications as well to, for
some improvement process in the future.
And someone could store a server that
runs AI to then do these And to add some
more detail, they could have the Linux
server at home in their, residence,
and they could have AI on that Linux
server reading the Fitbit data, and then
the AI would then be able to send the
phone notification to the individual.
And, we can add more context to this
apart from just the Fitbit data.
The-- We can add our
phone data in as well.
And then for the phone notifications
in the future, those can include
associations between, the wearable
data and the phone data and see you're
less active when you're on your phone.
You're more-- You have a higher heart rate
when you listen to music from your phone.
These types of insights could
be, potentially useful for a
per-personalized intervention.
And then taking it even a step further
and now saying that you can get your
smart home data connected to the,
Linux server you have at home and then
having the AI read the smart home data
as well and give even more insight
and have a better phone notification.
And then as you see where this is going,
you can connect like really so many
different devices potentially to this
like Linux server you have at home, have
the AI time to message and, have the
AI time to run at a certain time and
then go send a message to your phone.
And you w-- in order for this process
to work, we really need a server to
run at home to do all this and be
able to connect to all the devices.
And the thing is, this
process is relatively hard.
Just going from all the devices
to the Linux server is relatively
difficult 'cause everything has
its own API and data format.
If you're listening to this presentation,
you probably think the first solution
is running a swarm of AI agents.
I've done this test with like top models.
It's still very difficult.
It requires a lot of like steering.
It requires a lot of context.
You can still run into certain
issues with the data formatting.
The AI knows you're putting in
personal data, so it, tells you all
the time that this is maybe not safe.
And it's like pretty difficult to do.
Luckily, there is a solution.
It's one of the top open
source projects on GitHub.
It's called Home Assistant.
It has a huge number of stars, huge
number of installations and it's able
to take all your data sources and
put them in a unified SQL database.
And it can also set phone notifications.
It can do different types of
automations that you want.
It's a really, useful open source
project To touch on more of what Home
Assistant is, it's something that you
can install on any Linux server or
Windows server, and you can configure
it in your browser, so it doesn't have
to be a technical person to set this up.
You can-- It has its own app,
so you can view all the user
interfaces or anything on your phone.
This is where it can also connect
your phone data as well, and
it presents a very nice user
interface as is seen in the slide.
So it's very easy for people to use
So now the question becomes
how do we connect the AI model?
'Cause now we're able to collect
everything into one space
to set up this process which
was, originally the hard part.
Now, how do we get the AI model to go
read all the data and then send a phone
notification to help us walk more?
And this process is actually not
as trivial as someone would think.
It does involve writing a skill file,
but the specific details you add in the
skill file are gonna be really important.
It has to read everything, and from there,
if you have a lot of data sources, you can
tell it to read every single data source.
That takes a l- a lot of
time and a lot of tokens.
You can have it s- s- prioritize specific
streams as well if you would like.
You can have it implement
it in a certain way like the
specific design of the messages.
You can put information on how it
wants-- how you want it to evaluate
those messages and if they worked
or not, and then improve upon it.
For the AI model to run every day on
the server, we'd want the skill file
like this to run on like a daily loop
to then look at past notifications,
create new notifications, and so on.
And yeah, now we've created this
whole process where we've, selected
the first step, the personal data.
We have Home Assistant connect
everything, and then, we have our
daily AI skill that runs daily.
And then we have an intervention
decision that's made, and then a
phone notification later gets sent.
And this process works
relatively smoothly.
I actually use this process myself
for my Home Assistant, and it's
been working relatively well
And even now, going beyond phone
notifications, Home Assistant allows
you to connect to certain speakers.
It can connect to your computer.
It can create even go as far as
create personalized videos if you
set that up in the Linux server.
And that aspect is pretty interesting.
You can create personalized videos
for behavior change if you so
wanted to, and that's still a very
developing topic in the field.
And you can do things even beyond that.
You can have it set for specific
goals like meditation, sleep
diet, even other habits.
And you can really make the skill file…
You'd have to alter the skill file to
make it user selected to what you want.
And the nice thing about this is just with
the skill file, you can make these big
changes, so you don't even really need
to write software to do these things.
You just need to write basic text, which
is very nice And in conclusion I've shown
this way where we can connect all our
personal data through Home Assistant.
We can use the skill file now to then
guide those AI interventions, and I've
shown additional ways where you could
personalize the interventions to what
you would want and different ways where
you could intervene, and then for you,
evaluate what works in these situations.
Thank you.